Before we start, I wanted to take a minute to introduce
Joe Gilman. He is up there on our screen in the upper left hand corner.
He is the town's engineer.
And so
I had an opportunity
with with Eric and Jim to meet with Joe over since the last meeting, and
one of the things we were talking about was a gravel bit a little bit. I said we'd be cutting that at night, and I thought it would be nice for
you all to get to see the the person who's now our town engineer.
Yeah. So, welcome, Joe. Thank you.
The
first up is the roll call and seating of alternates and
I see we have Anne Purvey, Scott Razon,
Steve Nelson,
Leanne Hutchinson,
and myself,
all five regular members present. So, for tonight,
we won't be seeing any olderness.
Then we'll move on to item number three additions and changes to the agenda.
I've got three
small changes under new business five a
the property known as 17 School Road not 35 School Road.
And then we'll read letter.
The second item a the item B and the third
going to be item C.
Anybody
else have any
changes to the agenda or corrections to the agenda?
Hearing none, I make a motion to
agenda is I just modified.
Second.
Thank you, Steve, for seconding.
Any discussion?
Hearing none,
a call for vote in Yeah. Committee.
Actually think that it was open.
Dan?
Aye.
Scott?
Steve?
Aye. Leanne?
No.
Hearing
No?
>> Oh, I'm sorry. I thought I thought you're asking if there was any objection to adding these things? No. I'm asking for your
vote on passing the motion to accept those changes.
Oh, yes. Yes.
>> And I vote aye as well so the motion carries five zero zero.
I
think I
think all the public coming in is
probably going to talk about the school
application,
the community center application.
And so we'll let them come in and we'll we'll take their comments at that point.
I don't know you.
But do have any public comment before we start? I do not. Okay.
>> This is is Jake Serbia.
You're representing the application a which is on the agenda. Okay.
>> Thank you, sir.
Now did that application get posted?
Yes.
Okay.
I just
we're looking for it.
Welcome, everybody. We are
just at that point in the agenda where we are doing public comments.
And so
at this point, I'd like to limit any public comment for those items not actually on tonight's agenda.
And
hearing and seeing none out
out in the Zoom world, is there any public comment on an item not on the agenda for tonight?
Hearing none that completes
item four.
Public comment we'll move on to item five new business.
And the first item up is to accept the application for a special permit
set public hearing
on the property known as 17 School Road.
The applicant, the town of Andover,
seeking a special permit in order to construct a community center on properly property currently identified
as
School Road.
So
the application was was submitted last Friday.
So by the rules of our zoning regulations,
the application would be dated today, the twenty second or May.
And I did not intend to actually discuss the application tonight that will all be done at the public hearing, but we will take a look at setting the public hearing
tonight.
And I
wanted to run through the process that that I've seen before
before we start talking dates for the public hearing. So, you know, we we did have
an application submitted by the town for community center.
And
with that,
our regulations
require that we start a public hearing within sixty five days
of the receipt of the application.
Couple of things that have to be done before we can do the public hearing and so that sort of limits
on the earlier side when we can do that.
The public notice of the hearing must have published twice.
The first publication
not less than ten days or more than fifteen days before the hearing.
In the second, not less than two or more than ten days before the hearing.
The date published and the date of hearing are terminus days, and they are not counted
in that. So the earliest that we could could have a
public hearing
if if you were to get the, notice in the paper tomorrow would be in twelve days after the fall.
Which is around the fifth or the June 6.
Couple other things that that have to be done. We we have to send
the notice of a public hearing to the abutters around the property
and they have to be that goes out to be mailed out ten days in advance.
And we've got to put signs up, notifying the public to drive by the area about the public hearing, and those need to be up ten days before we go to public hearing.
So that's
that's the process that we go through. Once we start the public hearing, we have to complete it within thirty five days.
And once the public hearing is complete, we must back down the application within sixty five days after the public hearings closed.
I I know the town would like to go a little quicker than that on on the application,
and we'll
we'll try to do that without shortcutting
or or
not doing our due diligence
on the
issues that we need to address. So
my first concern was
not holding the public hearing
until the commission and zoning agent had a proper opportunity to review the package because it did. I
think I saw it online on Friday. Some people said they didn't see it until Saturday.
I
know we
well, so so
the commission members and and the zoning agent, I'm not sure if we've had if you had a chance to look through it, I could spend a little time over the weekend working through that.
But
I am going to try
and share my screen here.
You bring up the calendar.
There is the month of June, and so
I think that we could probably hold
a public hearing
anytime after the June 6.
I was interested in making sure that
our land use attorney attorney branch could be available for that,
and I
checked his schedule.
The
and I know he's available on either the seventh or the June 8.
One thing in the process that that I forgot to mention is,
you know, the Commission
might want to hold the sidewalk
out to to look at where the building is and and,
you know, that sort of thing.
The most efficient way to do that would be to do the sidewalk
just as it was done by some other folks have that before we started the public hearing.
And so
so that would be my recommendation on how we would do it.
At the public hearing meeting, we would start out with a sidewalk.
It it probably about 06:00.
It takes me a little while to get the computer and all that stuff set up. But once we get done with that and so I'd like to get
ready for that after we can start the public hearing at seven.
We heard from Scott that that he's available on the seventh. Any other
commission members have any thoughts
on on that
that date being a good one? The eight being a good one or is that too soon?
Anne, take your notes. You you might be sitting in the if
we if we go longer than the the seventh then.
>> Jim, can you can you do a go ahead, Jim.
>> I'm not positive. This room is available on those nights. I appreciate why that's why I want to look at the down calendar. Okay. It shows that the
only thing on the seventh is the young at heart meetings in eleven to March.
That was one of the reasons if you look at Tuesday, you can't read any of that stuff on the calendar up there. But Tuesday is a pretty full night here. And I think by Wednesday, we could have made sure that we have gotten
you know, the abutter letters out. We've got the notices properly posted
and
got the signs up and all that kind of stuff for our ten days. So,
I
think
the seventh would work good.
It
are you you know comfortable being able to do a thorough review of the application between now and then? Yes.
Any commission members think that
they would not be able to support that?
>> I won't be here, but I'm an alternate. So I don't Yep. Okay.
That's a good excuse. Hold on. I'm gonna be out of out of country then. Yep.
Okay.
>> With that
with that in mind, I would make a
motion that we conduct a sidewalk
on the
June 7 at 06:00,
followed by a public hearing on the June 7
here in the Community Room Hybrid again
at 07:00.
Looking for a second for that.
Any other discussion on
that motion?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote.
Anne?
Aye.
Scott? Aye.
Steve? Aye.
Weehan?
Aye.
>> And I vote aye as well. The motion passes
five zero zero.
The, I guess, while we're
talking about that, a little bit,
it's,
there's a good probability that
we wouldn't close the public hearing on the first first
second of the public hearing.
I am not available on the June 26,
which is when our next regular
meeting is scheduled.
So I was hoping to back that up to June
20.
Again, that date is open on the calendar here.
We
originally
the June 19 would have been our our normal
scheduled day.
But it's that's a Juneteenth
holiday.
I decided to
put that off went the following week with that had a conflict with my schedule. So now I'm asking the commission to consider
moving that date back to the twentieth.
And if needed,
that would be
the second, the continuation
of the public hearing at that point.
Okay.
Hearing no discussion on that.
I'll make a motion to schedule
a special meeting
for the June 20
to continue the public hearing as needed
and hold whatever discussion we need
to put on the agenda for that meeting.
That meeting would be at 07:00 hybrid just like we're doing now.
Okay,
Scott seconds.
Any discussion on that?
I repeat it. Yep. I got it. Yep. Okay.
Hearing no further discussion, I'll call for vote in.
Aye.
Scott.
Aye. Steve. Aye. Leanne.
Aye.
>> And I vote aye as well. So the motion passes
>> five zero zero. That will have a special meeting slash public hearing on the June 20.
The other thing that that we talked about while we're on the on scheduling
dates
and
we talked earlier about
shifting
meeting dates to the third
Tuesday of the month,
but to facilitate attendance by
our town planner.
And
so that would and
and so while the June meeting has to be a special meeting because we haven't
noticed it
thirty days in advance,
we can shift the dates of the other meetings
and have the thirty days notice
and
be able to go through the process that we would modify the agenda if we needed to do that, where we can't do that in a special meeting.
So with that, you know, the, the dates fall
fairly,
consistently
for the rest of the year here. The August meeting would be August 22 and September
would be the nineteenth,
October 17,
November 21, and December
19.
July meeting.
Thank you.
>> I think the eighteenth is the third two. Is the eighteenth the third one? Okay. Yep. And we'll do that too. When when I started making my notes here,
I wasn't sure if we'd be able to get two public hearing meetings in
in June.
And so I I didn't put
figured we need a little more discussion on that before we went in, but the the meeting would be the eighteenth. So
I'll make a note saying that we we moved the July through December meetings to the third Tuesday at one as we listed and,
vote for a second.
Second. Thank you, Steve.
Any discussion?
Hearing none,
we'll call for vote. Anne?
Aye. Scott? Aye.
Steve? Aye. Leanne?
Aye.
>> And I vote aye as well. Motion passes.
I think that that is all that I wanted to say about the
special permit
application for the community center.
I did promise that we would open for public comment at this time on that particular application
and
happy to hear
anything that anybody has at that point given that we're not going to actually talk about the application
until we get to public here.
Valerie?
>> Hello? I did send a correspondence
this morning when we wait meeting letter, we didn't allow more public
>> thank you and thank you your board email
all the commission members who've seen that I
I'm not gonna try this is my first go through on the hybrid meeting
And I
did pretty good getting the calendar up here. I'm not gonna try getting your email up there at this minute.
But
so that will be part of the public record and
as we go forward. Thank you.
That okay.
Any other comments
on the community center
at this point?
Okay.
Hearing none, we
move on to item five b.
And,
certainly,
you're
welcome to stay, but I think you all forgot other
things to do, and then we look forward to you to be in here. And I think it was the June 7 that we Thanks. Set up for that.
The
>> second,
application and setting of the public hearing,
Jacob Serdom,
87 Merritt Valley Road.
Applicant is seeking a special permit in order to operate a home based business plan stream.
Yes.
>> So, as you may say, yeah, as we said, I did not get a chance to review that application.
When did that get posted, Jeff?
Sometime over the weekend. Okay.
Okay.
>> I apologize for not seeing that. We're not gonna dismiss the application. It
>> got posted as a as an application.
It got posted online today.
>> Oh, I got it. Okay. That that thing. It was submitted over the weekend. It was posted online today. Yeah.
Okay. Okay. So.
>> So when is the date of receipt of that particular application?
>> I don't know if they're getting Friday or Saturday on campus.
Today today, I can give you date of receipt. The the date of receipt would be the next commission meeting.
Okay. Which is tonight. So
that's what I use.
>> So I guess even if the application came in electronically
today,
it could be
received
tonight.
>> It can the the commission has the discretion. It's always received within
twenty four hours. Okay.
Certified conversation with Mark Brits about that today regarding another application.
Okay.
>> Looking at
a public hearing for that,
since
with the commission
considering
an undue hardship,
If we
started a sidewalk,
does the commission
wanna do a sidewalk
over to
take a look at that or can we drive by
I have driven by you can you can see what you need to see pretty easily from the road.
So
what what's the commission
think as far as doing a sidewalk on that?
Any need for one or
or we all set? We
can probably get some photos and post those online
with the application
>> to have their changes
being made with this then or any changes in the property or just
allowing the space to be used?
The existing
>> is, as you know, I haven't looked at the application. So I don't know. I think I think the the
application is to
document and request permission to do what it's currently
already doing. Yeah. There may be some changes
that we wanna make
as a result of that. But
but I don't think, at this point, he would be changing anything
until
we might require another work or something like that.
>> For the record, did speak to the applicant
and asked that he provided
narrative
with some detail about the business as well as the checkups.
But what's included in the checklist, which we should be able to application. And hopefully, we'll we'll have that shortly. They post post post online.
>> So, Jed, do you think it's just a drive by will be adequate?
I do. You can
go on and talk too much about the application at a time, and you can see what there is to see
by the road.
Been
my question to you, Jacob, is that
I'm thinking that
timing is not of the urgent matter for you because we've been a while waiting to get the application
so far. You're just trying to get it resolved.
Correct. Yeah. So my my thoughts are that with the public hearing we're gonna do on June 7,
that might be a lengthy one.
And I would prefer to not have you have to sit through all that I would like to at this point put you off to the twentieth
which might be a shorter one
and
we would do the public
hearing for you on the June 20 at that meeting. Okay.
So
with that,
I'll make a motion that we schedule a public hearing
on the special permit for the home based business for Jacob Surgum 87
Merritt Valley Road for June 20.
And Wilkin for a second. I second. Okay. Thank you, Steve.
Any discussion?
Hearing none, call for a vote. Ian? Aye.
Scott? Aye. Steve? Aye.
Leanne?
Aye.
And I vote aye as well. That motion passes
by its
Okay. I think we have the number incorrect to to start with. New item five c, the structure changes to the regular meeting dates is already done.
So, with that in mind,
Jacob you're you're all set yes
you're ready to go and we'll see you on the plane
great thank you
>> next up
under old business is the application of William Genevieve special permit operating rapid and
with that
I'll turn that over to Jim. Okay this is an ongoing
>> project,
as you all well know. Currently, there's there's two remaining issues
primarily,
and
one is the direction of the
slope, the drainage slope.
And it's largely contained,
but I'm gonna want to address that. There is some that's that's flowing off from itself towards the Hutchinson property,
and I'd like to I've spoken to Joe Miller, our our country here, and he had agreed to to walk the site with me sometime in the near future
and
get a better handle on that. And the other issue is
the lack of education being established.
And I was hoping that that would transpire over the last few weeks and it hasn't.
So
that's the other issue. And in part, that's
probably
a
result of the fact that there's a lack of capsule,
which is called for in the original improvement plan. So again, I'd like to make sure that
to address that. And I have had some ongoing
dialogue with
the applicant and
the applicant's engineer.
They were invited to come this evening.
But I'm I'm trying to I did get a a
simple letter which was posted. I got a response which was posted. I have not responded to to that letter as of yet or any attention.
So there's few issues that are are unresolved at this point. We did the commission did give until the end of May.
I also have requested a copy of
the bond, which I was told is forthcoming,
and that's all I have.
>> Okay. So you you said the two issues were
drainage
and council for vegetative cover.
>> Yeah. And the the council and vegetative cover,
all the one
as one issue.
Really,
the direction of the current issues is the other.
I'd like to address that with all the plans and and and
and
building.
>> Okay, so
at this point,
you know, the restoration plan required, I think it was four inches of topsoil.
That sounds right. And how
much is out there now?
>> Well, there's I don't know exactly how much is in the in the front portion of the of the property, but there's next to none in the back towards the
the hill. Yeah. So it's pretty much here, and that's
based on the it's pretty hard. It's not that.
Based on walking on it. Yep.
I need to.
So I
>> to go out and check it out during the the little rainstorm we had
Saturday.
And
in
the rain was soaking into the ground just fine on Saturday. So we didn't get
didn't get to see too much there.
We did see the lack of topsoil
and.
So
what you said, what do we see is the way ahead
on this.
>> Welcome in.
It
discussed the direction of the flow and the amount of flow, but I'm
going back to the
the 08/15
approval, the 1522
approval
by the commission of a restoration unit.
That's what I have to go by right at this point in time.
In in concert with the original rule plan, they fill the conditions of the the original approval
in place.
Okay.
>> Now since the last meeting, I went back to the 08:15
Zoom recording,
and it it
starts maybe
an hour or so
into the meeting.
But I relistened
to everything, his
intention was to
have
no water.
I didn't hear
his intention was to have water go towards a little detention base in the center of the plateau,
and any excess
would flow off towards the extra mark and then back towards the third.
His most recent
letter that he sent, Jim,
was that,
you know,
know the runoff is 15% less than on the last plan.
In the last plan,
I thought it had zero. So I don't know how he got less than 15%,
but that's what Jim's gonna go out
and try to to figure out there.
And Joe, if
if,
you know, at some point,
you're hard up for something to do, you know, if you were to go back to that 08:15 Zoom meeting, I can send you I
can send you where it actually starts on that, you know, as far as the time,
but it is over it it takes over an hour of your time to listen through
the the day.
The the good news is that on
on the bench plan that he submitted, which he listed
in his letter to Jim, is the site restoration, the approved site restoration plan.
That was a drawing that I never seen before.
And so
I,
you know, and and once again,
you know, we're having a meeting where there's no applicant
and no engineer here. So the last time we had talked to
him was on
August
15,
which
it's a little frustrating that we've been, you know, coming up on another year, which was a year late on on when that was supposed to be done.
But anyhow, that
that is there and it would give you a sense
of what he committed to doing that.
My thought was that this other diagram,
I would have been
happy to
consider it if he had come to a meeting and talk to us about it. But did you show up or send it in and say, here's the approved plan?
I wasn't too keen on that
in in that plan still listed
four inches of topsoil everywhere.
Yeah.
>> And that's typically is that typically a standard too for vegetative
cover.
>> In the newer diagram had no topography data,
so
you couldn't tell
how big the detention bond was in the different sides and all that kind of stuff. The good news was
Catherine Hutchinson had some concerns about some things being removed
from the eight fifteen drawing that we talked about.
And I think all of Ms. Hutchinson's
concerns were incorporated
into that.
It
just been nice if somebody came to the commission and said, here's here's the updated plan based on the comments I took away from the last meeting.
We didn't get there. So
that's that and we did get an estimate that doesn't look like either the two proceeding.
So
there's a fair amount of frustration
with the graph.
First, Yeah. You can do other again, Joe, I'm just gonna give you the background so that I appreciate that. Thank you.
>> Yeah, look forward to listening to the the audio recording of the of the meeting from from August.
That'd gives us a good background and and Jim and I take a site walk out there to get a feel for
the lay of the land and the drainage patterns and the standard vegetative cover out there
to just get a handle on it.
>> Okay,
why did you see your
soil cover?
I saw none that I could
say was topsoil. You know, the the stuff up front looked pretty much like the stuff in the back of me. My thought was that at some point,
and this is speculation.
At some point during the grading over there,
they spread out the topsoil,
and then it wasn't graded properly
until they took everything out of that family and put it on the topsoil.
And so they lost it because
they didn't
follow the plan.
And
vegetative cover.
Would say maybe
5%.
Sorry.
>> In the letter, he said the total runoff area for the gravel pit
going towards the south of approximately 15%
less than the drainage area
on your food site plan.
Is he talking about the Central Basin?
>> I don't know he was talking about. And that's one of the problems.
Yeah, I think that's what he's referring to. Yep. And
Jim was trying to get in here so he could explain that to us.
Because neither Jim or I could figure out exactly what he was talking about there
and they were not. So.
What meeting should we next discuss this at? I'm reluctant to do that at the June 7 meeting
and thinking that might need to be at the June 20 meeting.
Privacy
I
>> know Mark Ranch is available for the June 20 if
we wanna have him here to
weigh in on that at all. But I
was trying to figure out, you know, at this point, it's really an unfortunate item for Jim to go off and do.
And I asked him, what what action does the commission have? And we
can free up the bond.
Or not and so
that
that gives us some leverage
there.
Jody, do you have any? Jody, can repeat?
Sorry, what?
Go ahead.
>> You Jed, could you repeat what you said
about two minutes ago or so about the top soil? You said something about it may not have been spread properly in the first place and then something about the grading
and then it looked to you like something else had been done after that could you repeat that part
>> yes so
is
you probably remember
there was
some point in time
where
somebody started reading.
And they weren't really doing it much in compliance
with the with the plan.
And it wasn't very high. Someway, we we recognized
that there were grading sticks
out there around the lot,
and they had blue lines probably two feet above where
the
the soil level was.
And if that was where the lot needed to maybe it's put put in, but if
that's where it needed to be graded to,
they had to move a lot of material
down onto that plateau.
I think that whoever was doing the initial grading
spread the topsoil out at that point in time thinking they were done.
And it turned out that they had to take all that material they excavated from the hill
and spread it around to get the elevations
correct.
And so my thought was they probably they might have spread the topsoil up earlier
and then covered it up with another foot or two of material they pulled out of the hill to get the the site up to the proper elevations that it needs to be to stay out of the floodplain.
In order to do what?
>> To get the elevation high enough so that it was properly out of the floodplain.
Okay. Thank you.
>> Okay.
Joe, did you have any questions or comments at that point?
>> No. I what you
described seems quite plausible that they maybe have lost some of the top cell through the process of regrading and reestablishing
grades, proper grades. But again, I'll do know, go outside, walk the site and get a good feel for where everything's at, at that point.
>> Okay. Yep. And I'm sure Jim would be happy to go out there with
you to to walk around.
Miss Catherine Hutchinson, I see that you are with us tonight. Did you have any comments at that point on
anything we've been talking about?
>> No,
these are points that I was raising in the limited time that I had to look at the material that was posted this morning.
And I think it's a very good idea
that
mister Dillon and Jim walked the site,
and
so Mr. Dillon can see things firsthand
and also would give him an opportunity to review everything
that all of us have been dealing with
over the
last several months,
if not years.
So I think it's very good idea.
Okay. Yep. Thank you. And I would like to, you know,
thank you for inviting me to comment because,
as you know, I'm very interested in the situation.
Understand. Yep. And thank you for participating.
You're welcome.
>> So that that
completes item
six, whole business six a.
Next up.
Because we're moving right along the amendment to the town zoning regulation.
So,
again, just
I've gone from
I've got everything on my desktop.
I've got the account issued laptop now so that I can
come
here and display
stuff and and that sort of thing.
But I'm not as well populated on this computer yet with with that. But since the last meeting,
and I think I said everybody
that I communicated
with attorney branch
on both the issue of
requiring one of the one
of the
property owners to be either the primary residence
or the accessory dwelling unit.
He said that probably not a clear cut, but he thought that was a good idea.
The other one that I asked him about was
now that we weren't going to do a special permit.
Should we
can we still put you know consistent with the rural character of the town in there?
And he said, well, you know, if if you were to get taken to court, you'd probably lose that one, but I would put it in anyhow just to, you know, try and
try and influence
that and begin to to be consistent.
You know one of the discussions I had with Eric over the last month was he he asked me if I was still planning to get rid of the special permit
thing.
And that again
I did that because it was consistent with the state. Said, I would be
I would be concerned about giving up that
ability
to control
what the accessory dwelling unit looked like.
And I thought that was a good point.
You know, we always have good points.
But then I said, what what
say do we have when a guy's going on to build a house
to make us consistent with the rest of the doubt? And if we had no say on the house,
I didn't think we were given up too much by the accessory apartment. So I said, I'm willing to take that chance. And if somebody puts something
totally ridiculous in this accessory dwelling unit,
I don't think they will because they don't want to lose their property values,
but
anything could happen, and we can always change the rules
back. But
I think most people, you know, they want to add something that looks nice. That's been our experience so far. We haven't had to weigh in on any of that at this point, so I was okay with that.
The other thing that that attorney branch
recommended, and I pushed back a little bit because it was pretty well spelled out in the public act that we couldn't do this,
where he said that his recommendation they're recommending all the towns require
that the accessory apartments be deemed affordable.
And his logic is that
any
rent
with
an accessory apartment is going to be very low in comparison to what a house rent would be. So it's not going to come close to that threshold for
being
in excess of that, not not a real hardship on anybody there.
And oh, by the way, we're not setting the world on fire on getting
our goal of 10 affordable housing
units
coming into being so far. So
I I said, okay.
He he offered to provide us a template because there's some
some work that goes along with that, and and I don't know what all of it is, but they'll give us a template to do to support that. And
and that's what I was looking for some feedback from you folks. And, Anne, you look like you had a question or comment? I have a question.
>> Seeing online and different things about different parts of the country, people are doing these tiny houses, and they're on wheels. Oftentimes, it's like a
a movable base
that they build a tiny house on. Would those be allowed or not in our
So
>> on that, and I'm not
an expert on that yet.
Some of that's
ground we have to go allow, but we did not opt out of
a
thing that the state issued for
caregivers.
And you can bring in
essentially a little mini trailer for your caregiver. That could be a family member. That could be a you know a professional
doing that kind of stuff and then when there's no longer the need for the caregiver,
the the little trailer goes away. We chose not to opt out of that a couple years ago. So, I'm thinking that that would be okay.
Yeah.
Start period of time.
Say again. A period
Period of time. Yes.
We we've also
we haven't spent any time yet
discussing
the states.
We're not allowed to prohibit
manufactured
homes,
which I think are
big traders.
And and we haven't started talking about that yet. And and I'm saving that for our new dental planner
to help out of that.
So
it's more more to come on that, but I don't think.
When you think about that, allowing somebody to live in a little trailer, you know, Jim is that you know he's going nuts trying to get people out of the trailers.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No. I was thinking about that because I know that just the common travel trailer that you would bring with you camping, say,
is not allowed to be used for for a house side of things. Right?
You've been chasing people out on that. But
these tiny homes
tend to be
settled into one spot and then not moved around. They're not taking camping, but people that live in this little tiny house.
And it seems to me they're about the size comparable to what we have for our accessory apartments, like the one where it's the little garage that's being made into a Yep.
So Accessory department. CBS
>> Sunday morning show yesterday. I don't know if they would watch that, but they they were talking about
design stuff, and they they started out with the highest penthouse
in the world in New York City, you know, 30,000 square foot penthouse
up there just in queues. And then they were they went down and they showed a couple of tiny house,
tiny apartments.
And they were talking on the order of 75
square feet.
As we saw with the except
the apartment we approved at the last meeting, you know, that was
I think maybe
200 or something.
And to me that looks small. But they had your the bed raised up into the ceiling and all this stuff. But you know, it was pretty
good. But
>> the weight of the future is tiny houses. It's less than four of these tables. Yeah.
>> And so
I'm not opposed to those. It's a question of coming through the septic system work and all that kind of stuff. And obviously,
you you can put a bunch of those in an area which our zoning regulations currently don't allow.
And so,
but as we get into the affordable housing, I think there's a growing market for tiny homes and not everybody wants one, but there's enough people to do that
that might be something we need to look into. So we'll we'll come there.
And I sent out
a
a list of comments from Jim.
Might be able to
so
I probably can't make that.
You probably all read it and and I'll
I'll put out the highlight here. Jim provided a couple of comments.
Minimum ninety day agreement for units.
I thought that was
okay.
Actually, everything
that Jim
suggested there,
I thought was
a good idea.
I wasn't too keen on the allowing basement apartments apartments to to exceed exceed the the established established percentage. Percentage.
Just because trying it's already too hard to make a rule,
you know, on on the size of the
accessory apartment, and I figured trying to do something different in the basement, just stick with whatever the rules are for accessory apartments and go with that.
But
if
we didn't have any
there.
Don't know how to make this thing zoom on my little touch pad here. I didn't look up the mouse, and so I'm not gonna try to get
that to to go. But
pad
anyhow, unless
somebody's got thoughts differently, here you know, I'll incorporate these comments into the draft stuff
we had
with putting in the, this stuff about the affordable units
and bring those back very quickly to see at some point after we make it through the community center
discussion.
But I didn't want to go too long.
You know,
that was good input.
I want to have that ready to go. But this is
we'll do that. It's 09:11.
So
I apologize for the inability
to read there. I didn't practice how to make the font bigger
before we got started tonight.
I'll try that again
When I had using your time to do that.
>> Okay. Question on the ninety days.
Around the lake, there are some people that rent out their homes for Airbnbs and things. Yep. And then there's some people that have apartments
above garages.
Are we saying that if that
apartment above the garage is accessory
dwelling within,
>> they can't rent out for a week or two at a time. But if you put your house in there to be, you can.
I think that's kind of
So I am not aware of houses or I am aware that there's some housing being rented.
We had talked about this some time ago and it wasn't a
concern for the commission at that point in time.
But it's
it
it's
if it's a conservative commission, you know, we can we can do that. Other towns have
taken some action like this.
My my thought was I wasn't gonna do it until it showed itself to be a problem like this minute. I think
it would be working okay.
Yeah.
But I didn't.
I do think that with
the accessory
department,
it was an okay prescription.
We consider putting in there. Jim's kind of was quite had it be legal, but I figured that's what Mark Ranch is for. They'll
they'll let us
know if we're running foul.
So far, his guidance has been, hey, it might be worth a foul, but do it anyhow.
Yeah.
>> I'm not saying it's been a problem at this point. I just wanna make sure we're consistent.
>> Yep.
Okay. Both the point to
that.
I
forgot
that there are some places in our Airbnb
around.
Yes. Yeah. There are people. There's at least one.
There's more than one. Okay. Yeah. I don't know.
Yep. And,
Again,
not a problem. And
I I don't have any complaints about it. I just if we're gonna restrict
Yeah. Don't mess with me. We are being so much.
Thank
you.
Any other comments on the
accessory apartment?
Okay,
the third item is the update status of contract for the township land and conservation development landing services.
The budget passed. So I think the next step there is
I will get with Eric and we'll get a meeting with John
from Tykey
and
have him show up in a meeting to
to meet us all and
figure out how we get started as a planet conservation.
One of the things that that that I do think is important,
you know, the original intent was to
focus very heavily on the planet conservation development. That's where we got that guy.
But as I look ahead to budget season next year, it would be nice to be able to say that this guy is a success story,
and we got nothing to show for it yet.
So maybe we could have him get some grants and that kind of thing, get more than paper salary.
And that way, everybody would think, okay. Yeah. That's that's not that bad.
And
make that so
so we need to figure out what what it is that
looks like a success story and then
ride towards that and make it some. And so, you know, try to shoot the region there about that a little bit so that we
can do that.
But we should be seeing him very soon.
I
>> guess
third thing before I forget it you know the other guy that I met and talked to with Jim over the last month since last meeting
was our new
building official
and
very nice guy
like I said you know we're named with Jim which is
you know improvement over what had been happening in the past not that it was the other guy's fault that he wouldn't get together with Jim and just overloaded with way too much going on and
that sort of thing.
We talked about the accessory apartment
building codes.
In one of Jim's comments is to put something in here that asked me to come.
But
who's the fellow named Rich?
Rich.
Okay. Okay.
He, you know,
he had
he he was taking seriously
making sure that the accessory apartments
are properly built. We we talked about,
you know, putting it on a a bed of stones and and all those kind of things and
you know, there's there's rules out there for that stuff and
but he's gonna be engaged by making sure that whatever accessory partner was built to code,
and I thought that was
pretty good outcome
for for us on that.
Is he dedicated?
He dedicated to.
>> Say again. Is he just for Andrew? He is a Paul or any Andrew. Okay. I don't know if there's any more than that that he's doing or not, but
but these, you know, these will actually look into set up
routine office hour here in the town hall, which I thought was, you know, something that we
then I'll make a motion to approve
the public hearing
meeting minutes.
From
>> Monday, April 17.
Okay.
And for May seconds,
any discussion on
the public hearing
minutes?
Hearing hearing done,
I'll call for a vote to approve. Anne?
But I had no comments on.
Maybe we'll keep you around for a while.
Item up is correspondence.
Jim, do we have anything there? No.
Done.
Okay. Administrative reports, Jim.
>> Okay. So my going enforcement
action.
I have Steve Barnett at 66416.
Housing code,
light,
and zoning.
More specifically,
a lot of junk on the property and monitoring it. It is.
It has been noticed. Seasons has
been issued
by the county attorney 03/21 we have on here.
I will be following up with Mark Grant on that.
The
housing code
enforcement
simply that the
house could
said the house might be occupied,
and it is not the primary quality on the property is not occupied. I do have an ongoing issue
with
folks living in the in the mobile home behind
or not the mobile home. I'm sorry. The the RV behind that.
And that's
hasn't
hasn't been resolved as yet. And I'm working with
both Ben and Brian and Mark on that.
Mark Grant's
haven't
seen any
progress on that as of yet.
So he ceases the system's time frame.
Okay.
The storage storage
set four five.
Four five twenty two edition.
Cease and desist was sent 11/14.
How will letter sent 03/08?
So I got.
the the gentleman with the defense next to the library.
I've been working with him to try and resolve that.
I got an email from him on
board three indicating that he
had painted some of the plywood and start
putting it out.
I don't believe he has as of yet.
I I I don't know that for a fact. I'm sorry. 243
Long Hill in house. I have yet to issue a letter on that. That is it's set way back. It's open. Absolutely not the market. I thought it was gonna take care of itself. It hasn't. I would love to get a letter out on that.
Asia and Marriott Valley had a burning business from residents.
Commission received
that an application
for both Volantis.
All application
seating,
so that is in progress.
64 Long Hill Road.
That's the property
on the
intersection really of Long
Hill and
and Wheeling.
And that's
it's not it's still open, but it's largely been resolved. Anybody who was fine.
The letter is going out actually from
the town attorney's office.
Just that there's there's still an hope there's an opening for the garage door plan
Long Hills and Bearswell. Yeah. The old
greenhouse is scope.
Three times far, we've had numerous conversations with Bill Byer, the owner, but an RV there as he indicated that it would be resolved
soon.
Haven't
had numerous telephone conversations with him, and I hope that it's taken care of in the next few weeks.
It was it's been locked up in every month, and somebody
shows to.
I don't know whether the match is what was approved or not. I
Okay. That is it. To our public works,
they have to prove it also. Right? Yes. He actually
got the message.
Yeah.
He we've been we we work with public
works.
Both
he signed up on
neighbor
and
sign up on the the location and.
If if we do.
But, I mean, I go back to the in this case, I go back to the renewal. The the subject plan, and, hopefully, there's there's a driveway in there. Okay. So they did without a permit. That's great.
He did. It's like yeah.
He
actually put a an anti traffic guy, and he's, like, supposed to. Yeah. Just
Okay.
>> Inland wetlands and watercourse liaison.
Once again, we had no meeting. So
that continues to be
pretty easy.
Next up on the agenda is public comment.
Anybody there that has any public comments for us at this point in time?
Joe, any comment for us at this point in time?
I'm set.
Thank you.
Dead.
I think we lost the audio
from you guys.
Yeah.
There we go.
Okay.
Yeah.
Leah, can you hear us from here?
I
>> can hear you now. I also lost it for a couple minutes.
Okay.
Did you have a comment?
>> No. That just that just that.
I don't know if you could hear me, but I couldn't hear you. Yep.
>> Got it.
So,
any other miscellaneous discussion?
Hearing none,
make the motion to adjourn.
>> Well, hold that one. I have paper paper plans for the community center for everyone over on this table over there. Okay. And I actually have paper applications.
I don't know whether anybody needs paper application because they can read those readily.
Read those online. The plans are not as easily read online. Those will be right there. To look at what's on the computer.